<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="sa" xreflabel="Security Advisories">
  <?dbhtml filename="sa.html"?>

  <title>Security Advisories</title>

  <sect2>
    <title>Security Vulnerabilities</title>

    <para>
      A security vulnerability, or a CVE, is a flaw in source code that can be
      used to harm the user(s) and/or the system in use, sometimes by abusing
      buffer overflows to achieve privilege escalation, modifying generated
      build scripts to use ssh at startup, or even messing with stale memory.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are many packages that push out updates that fix vulnerabilties,
      and some packages fix CVEs pretty often. GLFS will ocassionally have an
      update that upgrades a package that fixes a CVE. It's important to always
      upgrade packages on your system that contain security vulnerabilities,
      and there is a way for checking for those updates.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Checking for Security Updates</title>

    <para>
      To check for packages that have had a CVE fixed, go to the
      <ulink url="&lfs-website;/glfs/advisories.html">GLFS Advisories</ulink>
      page. It both covers broken changes and security information for each
      release.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can also go to the <ulink
      url="&glfs-issues;?q=is%3Aclosed+is%3Aissue+label%3Asecurity"> GLFS
      issue page</ulink> that has a filter enabled
      (<computeroutput>is:closed is:issue label:security</computeroutput>).
      All packages listed there that have the
      <computeroutput>security</computeroutput> label are packages that fixed
      a CVE in the version listed. Newer versions will be at the top of the
      list. When there are two versions of the same package, always go with the
      one that appears first in the list, or the top of it. Newer doesn't
      always mean safer, and it may sometimes be necessary to use an older
      version of a package, plus maybe a patch or two.
    </para>

    <para>
      Take note that in the latter method, the packages listed there are issues
      that have already been closed and are now in the book. You can go to the
      open section of the page to see if there are packages there that are
      still having details worked out and have yet to be fixed in the book.
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
